[Music]
Jamie so we did an interview about a
year ago now and it wasn't interview I
was expecting because you stealing fire
had come out - a couple of years ago now
all about flow state transformational
culture and what I was expecting was an
interview about kind of the value of
transformational culture and kind of how
flow states are essential for evolution
and all of the stuff that isn't stealing
fire and what you actually did was
poured a kind of big bucket of cold
water all over that idea and just said
hang on whoa whoa whoa whoa we need to
be careful because we've got all of
these tools but we're not using them
properly and it looks like we're going
to make some of the same mistakes that
everyone's always made with these
technologies how have you changed in the
last sort of year since we spoke last
time yeah I mean I would love to say
that was just you know whistling past
the graveyard moment but no I think I'm
actually far more pessimistic and
concerned actually in ways that I didn't
even anticipate coming out of stealing
fire they were there was some sort of
obvious known issues that in the
documenting of hey there's this
revolution in non-ordinary states and
not just flow States but you know
meditation and smart tech and
psychedelics and kind of just pretty
much every way in you can imagine people
are starting to crack that code and put
those things together combine them and
do all sorts of things and at the time
I'd laid out three potential sort of
known pitfall areas the first was
commodification the idea that being able
to hack our neural chemistry are sort of
the biology of bliss that it could be
used to sell us more and absolutely
100% you know hasn't is in increasing
quantities and the move into vrn AR and
algorithmic social media and all those
kind of things is pretty well-documented
most folks are actually more aware of
that now and it's happening anyway the
other words weaponization then saying
hey state actors with massive budgets
are super interested in super soldiers
and super interested in everything from
mind control to performance enhancement
that this whole range and again you know
has been going on for
half-century plus and is simply we would
just predict it would continue but the
third one was sort of our own worst
interest are the hedonism and that
element what he that element has shown
up far more virulent Lee than anything I
sort of anticipated and it really does
feel that the sort of psychedelic
Renaissance or the stealing fire
revolution whatever I want to call it is
really just showing up as a Children's
Crusade these days and there's an awful
lot of people kind of rushing in and we
are actually you know finding ourselves
a being led by people who don't know
what they're doing be in the you know
the steepest part I've kind of you know
that got in a research groups hype cycle
idea that you know there's the there's
the peak of expectations followed by the
trough of disillusionment and then you
know over time you kind of slowly and
gradually get back to what's actually
gonna be the steady state promise and
delivery of any given movement
technology etc and so I think we are
literally almost at the high point and
just teetering on the brink of the crash
which I would probably timestamp as
anytime in the next 18 to 36 months we
would anticipate a collapse along a
series of kind of fairly predictable
vectors and what do you think that crash
is gonna look like well I mean I think
you can take it probably macroeconomic
medical professional and then sort of
social and so speaking that now if we
can a narrow the focus from a sort of
over a broad revolution in ecstatic
techniques and technologies and that
kind of thing he likes actually get down
to specifically you know what Michael
Pollan is written about is the
psychedelic Renaissance what its kind of
you know really bubbling to the surface
these days the first is it's not going
to look anything like what the early
revolutionaries ambassadors and
advocates hoped or wished and that's
just kind of table stakes things never
do you know if Benjamin Franklin and
Thomas Jefferson looked at the 2016
election they'd be like what the
everliving just happened right and
even
mentor if I was John Mackey he was the
founder of Whole Foods you take the
example of those guys and a little bunch
of little you know anarchist hippies in
1982 or 1983 in Austin Texas you know
building a health food store and it was
Birkenstocks and big bulk bins so you
know bulgur and carob and that was their
thinking and now it's you know now it's
$20 a pound
artisanal goat cheese and a plug-in for
your Tesla's and your Lexus hybrids you
know on the one hand you would say if
you were an idealist from back at the
inception of that thing you would say
this is an utter corruption mutation
this is not what we thought or what we
wanted but on the other hand Whole Foods
at least prior to Amazon acquisition
right Whole Foods has been an absolute
global market maker in organic foods and
additional companies like Trader Joe's
like Costco even Walmart is now that has
the largest private label organic brands
none of that would have happened were it
not for that Whole Foods growth are
concurred into the thing it you know one
of the inception could have seen so just
as a general premise whatever this turns
out to be it is probably not gonna look
anything like people at boom fest or
people at Burning Man or even the kind
of you know elders of the 1960s
movements would have imagined hoped
wanted or even recognized as their own
offspring so let's just assess that and
you know wouldn't know know know battle
plan survives first contact with the
enemy and nor does any disruptive
technology but at the you know and
actually along those lines one of the
simplest things that we will see as
we'll see captured by Big Pharma so you
know most cyclic compounds you know
beyond patents they're all expired
they're all open source which has no
interest in innovation and no interest
in the ability to capture and set
pricing so what we've already seen is
things like ab a-- dialects their first
synthetic cannabinoid that has now been
approved for seizure use epileptic
seizure used we've just seen the the
approval by Johnson & Johnson Avice get
amine so an intranasal
I mean a variation and we connect we
would expect and anticipate much much
more of that that there will be the
attempt to come back in with large R&D
budgets large IP protection tweaking and
modifying molecules in order to get it
back into the stack of Big Pharma
product launch development price setting
etc and again as we said already seeing
that happen and we should expect a lot
more of that in conjunction with that
we'll probably see again to the chagrin
of the revolutionaries we will see a an
isolation and a backing out of many of
the subjective you know qualities that
aficionados or enthusiasts see is
central so if you look at the World
Health Organization's descriptions of
ketamine and nitrous adding the nitrous
oxide even just take those two
experiences they will be able to you
know in one line they will say you know
known side-effects you know excess
ideation and you're like yeah that's
actually why all all non-prescribed
users are using this stuff by the time
you get it into a the medical industrial
complex right those are actually seen as
as problems to manage not central
reasons to to do and so what we will
quite likely see in addition to the
tweaking of molecules for patentable and
controllable process and price setting
you will also see an isolation of
basically biomedical input so for
instance ketamine on the one hand this
tends to disclose at high doses
profoundly strange and either you know
terrifying or deeply valuable depending
on your experience in your disposition
interior realms and domains on the other
hand it's a excitatory glutamate
receptor site anti-depressive ish so
what we will see as we'll see the look
the isolation and the focusing on
certain biomechanical mechanisms of
action and often the the partitioning or
the minimization of some of the interior
subjective ones that are typically what
everybody thinks of when they think of
psychedelics so that will be happening
and what you could broadly say is we
will see you know we
wanted you know we sort of we we thought
we were getting Woodstock and we're
going to get prozac nation in 2.0 for
the time being it's a very high margin
high ten of a product to be pushing so
if you take for instance ketamine
clinics which are now booming in the
United States I think there's over three
hundred the last time I checked it's
probably more now and there's a lot of
other companies coming in and looking to
do scale rollouts
a huge part of that is that the floor
typically for ketamine therapy is five
hundred bucks an hour and the ceiling is
anywhere from a thousand to fifteen
hundred dollars an hour depending on
location and kind of service level so
you have an awful lot of people just
being like oh that's actually good
chin you get you get lots of people in
and out and you get very high dollar
very high margin relatively easy things
sit here let me a jab in an ivy off you
go and you can make sure you're okay you
can you can summon an uber or a lyft and
and you know you're safe as houses so
there are right now quite strong market
incentives to pull more people into this
space than may have the grounding
experienced ethical orientation or sense
of the nuance and the complexities of it
at the same time you also have you know
an in do in some part due to that driver
it's a good way to make to do profitably
decent things for patients you also have
you also have sort of psychedelic
novices in the helping professions
coming into whether that's a general
practitioner MD or even a trained
psychiatrist so we were actually at a
Maps I was speaking in a Maps benefit in
a not too long ago and sat at a table
with a really well-intentioned
psychiatrist who had been coming up
through conventional Western medicine
had not surprisingly found that tools
for anxiety suicide depression weren't
always working were looking for
additional tools and had literally come
to it from a very kind of conventional
stepwise professional inquiry and had
attended a ketamine licensing there
you know therapy protocol and part of
that was one experience with ketamine
themselves so they can you at least a
little bit about what they do and that
was you know twelve months prior so this
this is a person who had no prior
exposure to psychedelics so psychedelic
novice one exposure for their own
experiences of ketamine and then jumped
into administering it and they had all
kinds of surprises that you know that
they had patients who didn't who were
freaking out when they had their first
kind of slipping of egoic self-reference
screaming and shouting they didn't they
basically just had no idea the waters
they were wading into and yet they were
the licensed and certified professionals
so back to your kind of known
side-effects or exercise even versus
that is the whole point we have a lot of
folks not knowing what they're getting
into getting it into it for economic
kind of business model reasonings and
not necessarily an understanding of how
to skillfully Midwife patients through
that experience if you're really just
thinking take this medicine it does an
igloo to make excitatory response we're
not quite exactly sure how it works but
it seems to have at it and then all the
other things all the interior content
that's coming up we don't actually have
a place for that we don't have a place
where in our service model we don't have
a place for it in our integration and
off to care and we don't have a place
for it in our own minds and experiences
that's going to set up for a lot of
problems and then not combined
compounding on all that so you've got a
gold rush into the space you've got
under informed people administering with
less than fully supportive integrative
protocols because they literally don't
know what they don't know and they're
treating this as they would any other
prescription pharmaceutical take it
watch the side-effects go home call us
in the morning kind of thing and you're
then you're also seeing predictably this
is is this Clayton Christensen Harvard
Business School you know talked about
market disruptions and how this happens
people come in at the top with high maje
and high dollar stuff and then there's
kind of a rush to a bottom and there's
disruptors that come in well what we're
already seeing and I've just just had
someone send this I just kind of read
this a couple of weeks ago somebody sent
this in my inbox
we're seeing novel adaptations to the
business models so there's a group who's
now looking to do ketamine therapy which
is typically like best practice
protocols for that six sessions for
three to five thousand dollars right and
it's usually it's a batch you kind of
you buy it you pay it up front it's not
always covered by insurance right so
it's high cash cash up front
and then you get that experience well
now there's a group that's looking to do
$900 you come in you have your first
ketamine session in an office with
direct oversight blood pressure cuff you
know monitoring and after that you got
take home loss news so you're like okay
so now there's gonna be a rush to the
box that we got a gold rush and we got a
bunch of people piling it and I won't
have massive public availability and a
lot more people both clinicians and
patients coming into this experience at
the same time that all the margins are
getting massively undercut and there's
gonna be a race to the bottom so quality
of care the sophistication and
complexity of what can be done because
how many dollars do we have to devote to
this you know against existing medical
models of just pop a pill go home you
know we're not even gonna do talk
therapy anymore because that doesn't
work out that doesn't pencil out on the
health insurance you know codes we're
likely to see an erosion of care and an
erosion of support and it will become
more and more transactional at the very
moment that it actually should become
more and more integrative and holistic
the final one is just the social so
what's happening outside and Big Pharma
what's happening outside of the medical
clinical professions and and what are we
seeing just in the level of enthusiasts
who are now sort of hashtag because
science you know they're seeing these
studies that they're taking this
research as validation of their own
extracurricular efforts and explorations
as well as the entire gray market
economy that fully lives are in in that
space and so we're seeing I mean back to
that idea of the Children's Crusade
we're seeing
basically narcissism hedonism and
commercialism showing up in the social
sphere as well and and so the narcissism
is is one I didn't I didn't I just
didn't anticipate the virulence with
which this is happening but you know
that that sort of idea of you know
they've done a fair number of studies
these days with like the rise of super
flus because of the excess prescription
of antibiotics
alright so doctors are just like Oh in
and out you know you see you've got the
sniffles you see you've got a cold I
don't even care because I know that a
you'll leave my office quickly if I give
you a prescription B you'll rate me more
highly on my online thing so I'm just
gonna give you antibiotics and everybody
knows that if you start taking
antibiotics even if you feel symptom
free you should keep taking them to the
end right because otherwise that tiny
little leftover of bacteria or whatever
it can come roaring back worse than ever
and so because of that over the last
several decades we've created super
viruses super flus and and it's the over
prescription of antibiotics and you
could make a fairly clear case that
we're in that neck of the woods with
psychedelics - which is that people are
taking them and they're getting almost
rid of their egos and not quite and
they're staying their symptom-free
they're like I'm a golden God whatever
right I'm going to open my own workshop
I'm gonna do this thing and that that
egos are coming roaring back more
virulent than ever so we're getting
super egos and not only is that
literally just you know a case of people
not having any lineage background not a
sense of discipline on a sense of the
length complexity nuance difficulty
actually fully growing up as people just
developmentally informed kind of
psychology juxtaposed against lineage
practice but it's also being amplified
by social media loops so now are having
people you know no sooner are they
having an experience of ego dissolution
or so you know whatever might else occur
in these spaces then they are composing
their social media posts and snapping
selfies here's me down in the jungle
watch you ma you know Oh amazing or
here's me at Burning
or here's me just coming out of my
ayahuasca retreat in Williamsburg and
whether it's the prevalence of folks
like Joe Rogan and things like that
where you have public pod public figures
effectively openly talking about these
things plus the ability for me to then
share and virtue signal of my great
latest breakthrough or my latest insight
or just us living the life that is
absolutely re skinning our egos faster
than we're able to get rid of them and
you can see that I mean the simplest
example you know you're familiar
probably with like the Museum of ice
cream and those kind of interactive you
know museums and installations around
the world that are popping on these days
and they're they're fun they're
whimsical they're cute but what they
really are
Instagram backdrops you know so people
are going less to be immersed in the
actual moment and the actual delight
than they are to be capturing it in a
very contrived fashion for an audience
that's not co-located with them it's
it's for digital digital selves and I
noticed that I didn't know what I was
looking at actually when I first saw it
but three four years ago there was an
inflection point at Burning Man and you
know if folks are familiar with that
it's a it's an outdoor festival in the
desert and the desert is you know it's
one of the Salt Flats so it's completely
a flat white expanse and there's you
know one of the most compelling things
about that place is this these
larger-than-life art exhibits and so
this white flat does it becomes
effectively like an amazing gallery and
their giant there they're just oversized
you know 50 feet tall 60 feet tall giant
things and they're almost all
interactive there's something about the
art it's not to be passive and go boom
yes I learned his use of color and
composition and form you know you engage
with you hang on it you swing on it
there's a joke there's an interaction
there's something that shifts your state
they're all psychedelic odd in that
respect or ecstatic out in that sense
and what's what's been happening in the
last few years you really know this
is just the Museum of ice cream in the
desert
people are just literally coming up to
up not not interacting with it as humans
not not allowing themselves to be moved
or transformed by it but literally just
using those backdrops for their own
social media profile so digital
Gnosticism
has overlaid with the psychedelic
Renaissance in ways that is and it's
it's a little bit like that cut Vonnegut
but cat's cradle you know where I sign
is that weird molecule that can freeze
all of all water molecules on the earth
and basically end life right and it
almost feels like it's digitally fuel
psychedelic Gnosticism is like ice 9 it
is just encasing our world in super egos
faster than we can actually melt them
and that's horrifying you know
there's like these are arguably the most
powerful tools that humans have ever
assembled
to get out of ourselves and yet these
other tools we've built all right which
leaves us in the echo chambers of
ourselves have actually co-opted that
enterprise and so that's yeah that's
that's a horrific thing the next is just
kind of hedonism which is again
permission with with the psychedelic
Renaissance with all the profound work
that's happening with maps and Imperial
College and a lot of the other folks
that are just heads down doing an
amazingly ethical principled work in
service of the people who are hung out
to dry I mean the people who are just
suffering from debilitating trauma and
anxiety and depression and suicidal
ideation they're just really you know
out of out of options there's that
profound and beautiful work and you know
and we wrote about it in stealing fire
the idea that one two three sessions of
mdma-assisted therapy for instance can
just profoundly take a load off somebody
who's been carrying those buttons
themselves without help without relief
it's beautifully uplifting but the
reality is is that 33 or 303 sessions
you know off-label done on my own time
done recreationally or even with an
attention there's an asymptote of return
on investment
those folks are 10 times has changed or
transformers that people have done it
once or three times and so my sense is
is that there's increased permission you
know that because science I'm micro
dosing because science were tripping on
the weekends because science and I
and there's a sort of absolution of well
are we making the most of it are we
integrating this is this actually
leaving me a better person or are these
just different bright lights to go chase
is this just a novelty is this just
chemically-induced well-being that is
fleeting and we're not actually doing
the work around it and the final one is
just commercialism or commodification
which kind of is the first to the the
narcissism plus the hedonism plus
commercialism which is the idea that in
this age of you know anyone can be an
expert and all you need to do is publish
an e-book and set up a blog and you know
put out and put out a shingle and have
an evite and see you see what Guppies
come there is this the disconnect
between depth of experience
apprenticeship humility to the vastness
of the psychedelic realm let's say and
people's absolute brazen willingness to
dip their toe in it to claim the mantle
and to turn around and show their
expertise to other newbies and newcomers
so I've you know I'm an apprentice in
training or I'm a shaman in training
what you've been to prove twice or maybe
three times and you've chucked a bunch
at home and you're now actually
presuming to lead people through
experiences that you've barely begun to
fathom yourself and if you think about
like in which we're seeing this trend in
in both places you know like what's
happening the psychedelic realm is also
happening in extreme sports where you're
having more and more people toe into
jaws this giant wave in Maui
you know because they've seen it on Red
Bull and they have no business they
haven't come up through the ranks of
Waterman you know they want the selfie
water what's called GoPro courage you
know and we're seeing you know the same
with mountaineering there are people on
8,000 meter peaks now who literally are
summiting you know with a guy dragging
them up short ropes just literally can
go like a dog on a leash I mean
connected two carabiners in the harness
in a literally getting dragged at the
mountain and it's time to rappel off the
summit and they've never rappelled
before you know so you're like what on
earth is going on you know people are
big
largely because of social media they are
ending up in places they have no
business being but now we're even
getting to the place where people are
presuming to lead others from that spot
and it's the sense of can I gain money
fame privilege prestige there's that
there was a particular infra marketer I
saw there just made me cringe they was
talking about you know we will take you
down to to Peru we're gonna host a
medicine journey a retreat where you
will download wealth codes right and
we're the ones to help you and we have
coached dozens of people to million
dollar business and all this is shot
selfie infomercial style as I walk
around my rented mansion in Bali telling
you that we've unlocked the universal
source codes of abundance and we too can
help you for as little as a ten thousand
dollar retreat so you know the last
gasps of cultural appropriation as well
as you know in the kingdom of the blind
the one-eyed shall rule and we're seeing
a ton of that as well so that's kind of
those are just the factors I'm watching
you know and and and I would imagine
that I mean a they're all already
happening so none of this is sort of you
know
Cassandra you know magining worse
scenarios are saying well what if that
happens these are all already happening
the question is just where do they lead
us lots to pick up on the one thing from
from earlier you mentioned that the
there's a sort of bifurcation where
medicine is looking for the the medical
effect while not being interested in the
the psychedelic effect a lot of people
in the psychedelic medicine space would
say that the those two things are
together like the the especially was for
example psychedelic mushrooms that
feeling of oneness that internal
subjective effect is the therapeutic
effect so with most of them that's not
going to be possible is it to
disassociate to to bifurcate those two
things yeah and I think it's I think
it's great that a number of the
therapists that are working in this
space are actually and somewhat
strangely within Western clinical
medicine courageously saying it's some
of these interior experiences that are
actually valuable and we need to notice
them
and build our protocols around them and
the question will simply be to what
extent does that persist here's again
with large pharmaceutical companies
tweaking molecules they're good that
that's actually a messy aberration the
interior subjective experience is not
clinically controllable and manageable
so wherever possible and this is you
know as we've seen with epidemics right
here's a cannabinoid rather than just
like here's cannabis that grows out of
the ground or grows in a greenhouse and
it works they're like oh get away that
pesky hi let's isolate it isolate
isolate it to do the one thing for the
disease case that we're trying to solve
for chop it all up repackage it rebrand
it and mock it up so that will be a
question as to how long that persists
does that now grow because that's
actually the truth of the matter which
is that majority of the healing is
actually changing my relationship to
myself and to my narratives and what's
happening on a neurochemical and even
neuroplastic level are the structural
correlates to that change or are we
gonna try and wring out those those
known side-effects to create a more
manageable process in the sort of
industrial medicine thing so that's you
know tbv
but obviously you know full hats off to
the folks that are taking a stand for
that and I know that some of the people
so I've done quite a few pieces about
psychedelic medicine over quite a few
years and I know that there's always
been a sense of this tension between the
scientific model and the experience
itself and I know that some people even
within psychedelic medicine are having
their torn because they're thinking well
we have an idea and some of the results
that have come out from the latest one
in the UK was Robin Carhartt Harris a
lot of the the people who went through
it had a they were relieved of their
symptoms of depression for sort of three
months at a time but then it would it
would often come back and this sense
everyone who's taken psychedelics kind
of knows that yeah we get this after go
period
you have to put in some changes to your
lifestyle or changes to your your your
lived experience in those three months
if they're going to be sustainable so
people are being forced into a medical
model that maybe is not helpful to them
creating meaningful change in their
lives and meaningful change for their
conditions yeah I mean if you take the
most kind of extreme boundary case I can
think of which is something like
psychedelic like five Meo
DMT which is you know arguably and I
don't think many people actually argue
this is you know the most potent
compound that humans have ever had
access to and you come across folks who
have anecdotally had you know one
experience three experiences five
experiences and I've been kind of
watching over the last five years like
and.and you know people come back you
know hair on fire for you know this
amazing exposure to what some people
just say is literally unmitigated you
know submersion in you know filling your
superlative you know consciousness like
god had the you know the universe
ultimate true coming true like burning
bush Ark of the Covenant you know level
stuff and I haven't seen a single one of
their personality structures structures
shift and in fact particularly kind of
west coast New York you know that
convert that the kind of chattering
classes who are most able to access this
stuff it almost feels like it's just one
more bobble to hang on the Christmas
tree and like like going to a hip you
know how did you get front-row tickets
to Hamilton and that is pretty sobering
I think and should put the rest of it in
context which is is if you know if you
go to developmental psychology you can
see Bob Keegan at Harvard University
folks you know people have been studying
this stuff for decades and really taking
a look like human change and adult
development is hard and slow and iffy
and there's no specific or singular
intervention that absolves us of that
incremental work and if you have a peak
breakthrough experience I mean a you
know what going up we're going to the
waterfall with thimbles so in some
respects the the access
of information that typically comes
through in a psychedelic state there's
only there's only a fraction of that
that we actually can sort of bring back
into our waking state consciousness and
into our lives and in fact sometimes
it's contraindicated that there is no
point getting lobbed to a hundred
thousand feet if you can only breathe
down to the first twenty to 26,000 feet
so there's a lot of overshooting the
mark of what can I translate into my
life and then there's often a lack of as
you said you know the hard dedicated
work of integration that particularly
when it's so much more tempting to go
back to the Wishing Well right versus
doing the shitty hard stuff and that
people are often neglecting that even
more when they have these quick little
bypasses if I can only get to that place
after two decades of meditation practice
for instance it's slow it's distractive
no one's got time for that these days
there's a whole lot of reasons why
traditional monastic practices or
martial practices may or may not fit
perfectly with pell-mell 21st century
society but they had some checks and
balances in them and you had to have
prepared the vessel before you pour it
in the sort of water of life now we're
just swimming splashing around and
spilling tons because anybody can get
there with very little effort and as a
result and we're not balancing it with
the with the work afterwards what do you
think about the the mix between the
scientific model and psychedelic
research it seems like an awkward fit
however you spin it sure I mean you know
you end up with sort of pee hacking and
placebo effects you know so basically
the idea that double-blind
placebo-controlled studies I mean eight
don't work that well in psychedelics
because you really know in a heartbeat
whether you've got the fake one or the
real one and so even when they've done
you know like take niacin instead of
psilocybin so you get kind of a flushing
and a tingling but no psychoactive
effects it's pretty hard to cram
psychedelic research into that specific
pharmaceutical trials model the other
element is
the interior subjective experiences
which are arguably a large chunk of the
value and impact of these things don't
subject themselves to controlled
measurement you can do subjective
analysis and surveys and things but
again what are you tracking are you
tracking like a mystical state inventory
okay what wild-ass crazy did I see
while I was there okay
useful but not definitive are we
discussing behavioral change shift in
adult developmental complexity if so
that stuff doesn't often change that
fast or if it does momentarily have kind
of a an off to glow effect it's going to
return fairly close to baseline and
you're really Nikken you can pick things
up like long-term stage development
maybe in a six month window but usually
it's 12 18 36 months or longer to really
see the arc if someone growing up as an
adult and so our tools and our timelines
just clinical trial and how long were
you in them don't don't particularly
submit to that and if it's a multi
variable equation that creates the
transformation which is I mean even just
take it out of the labs what what
happens where somebody might have an
epiphany you might be in the rainforest
with an indigenous shaman traveling out
of your country out of your language out
of your comfort zone different
bioregions all those things combining to
have the ayahuasca experience you had or
if you're at a transformational festival
and there's light in this sound and
there's music and there's companionship
and those are these things and a
psychedelic compound and it was the
entire thing that of that evening or
that day or that week or whatever was
that cracks you have been how do we back
all those things out and so my sense is
is that we probably need different
research protocols if we're really going
to try and sort of F the ineffable if
we're going to really try and pin down
what is the juju or what is the
transformational magic and how can we
both understand it better and help more
of it happen more healthily for more
people it would almost be the sort of
the kitchen sink method which is figure
out all the factors that for sure crack
people wide open
study that and then you just can back
off back off individual elements until
you get an undesired drop-off in
efficacy and that's a that's a different
way of doing it but I think we can't we
can't think that atomizing elements and
measuring them in isolation ever adds up
to the mystery we might need to start
with the things that we know for sure
deliver glimpses of the numinous and
then we know those are there and then we
can start figuring out you know reverse
engineering or sort of almost regression
analysis what were the elements that
were overwhelmingly contributed versus
just kind of nice window dressing and do
you think that psychedelics can ever be
offered within a Western medical
paradigm well I mean I think I think the
medical paradigm was essential for
socio-political legal reasons and that's
why there's been enough that's why there
was an initial emphasis on treatment
resistant depression anxiety those kind
of things because that's actually how it
works it works within the legal codes it
works within the system to say okay if
these people are absolutely out of
options then we might allow something
more radical or innovative etc the thing
that we're missing is is why would we
why would we use it what is the ethic of
use what is the orientation and it feels
to me like at a minimum there's at least
like three super functional uses for
Peak States in general I mean
psychedelics are a use case but they're
not the only one but it's the idea of
like first of all as metronym you know I
am out of step with life the pulse the
rhythm but I can't quite I don't know
for sure right I'm busy I'm hectic I'm
distracted I'm all these things and I
drop in to a psychedelic State or any
other you know skillfully produced the
ecstatic space and I'm like oh this is
where the one is this is where the
metronome is telling me the beat is and
I can cook I can correct I might have
been half half a beat late I might be in
half a beat early whatever it is I can
correct
and now I'm on the one and the next one
is cheating for you know again running
and going through life we bump into
things we get hit we get hurt our
instrument our bodies our brains our
hots our minds gets knocked out of whack
and we're just suddenly we think this is
a sieve and it's actually C sharp or a
little bit flattened really oh okay I'm
trying to play with others but I'm
actually sharp or flat let me tune my
instrument and so the metronome and the
tuning fork do a beautiful job of that
and if you think you know to continue
the musical metaphor musicians all use
metronomes and tuning forks but they
don't spend their entire day fiddling
with knobs and strings and flipping the
pendulum back and forth the moment
they've got the one and the moment
they've got a clean sea they go off to
make music they either practice it
themselves or they go jam with others
and I think that's the relationship we
really need with psychedelics not that
we just constantly you just hit the bell
hit the bell fiddling on spit all the
knobs and the ideas like get yourself in
tune get yourself on time go jam that's
the point the point is to go make the
music of life together and you know the
final one it's a little bit just sort of
training wheels and I think this is one
where the once in a blue moon
psychedelic experience you know once in
a lifetime once a year whatever it would
be needs to be supplemented because what
we're missing I think this sort of the
the weekly Sabbath can we dust that
bastard off and reinvigorated because
getting to once a month that once a
season you know solstices equinoxes
whatever the hell you know take your
pick on calendar preference but what do
I do
recurringly and periodically because one
of the things that the recent you know
that the research that maps been doing
with MDMA therapy right is that it does
something very specific it shift your
neuro chemical profile and actually Rick
Doblin was just sharing with me the last
time he and I talked that the closest
neuro physiological analog they've found
to somebody in an MDMA therapeutic
dosage session is post orgasm and it's a
state of CC 18 right you have you have
oxytocin you have prolactin right you've
got an increase in serotonin basically
feelings of safety so
purity belonging well-being and that
that actually allows people to relax
their vigilance response turn off their
amygdala and their their threat scanning
and be and have a little bit of distance
between themselves and their stories and
their past pains and that that alone can
be transformational so what is it like
for us to have to supplement the once in
a blue moon there's no deep psychedelic
dives with the idea of what are we doing
one day out of seven what are we doing
one day out of 30 or 90 and can we use
those experiences to defrag our nervous
systems and really open our hearts and
expand our minds and say okay now I've
got a sense of this I have a somatic
marker for how this feels
can I use this experience as training
wheels can I actually go into the next
day the next few days even how long can
I keep this up how long can I practice
living from a more courageous more
vulnerable more open state until that
becomes muscle memory until that becomes
as familiar right as my old contract in
reactive State and I think that that's
that combination it sort of shoot the
moon once in a blue moon I integrate the
hell out of it and every and much more
regularly in smaller doses can I do the
metronome tuning for training wheel game
and live into the better angels of our
nature
live into what's what what my highest
most generous expensive self might be
and if you've been documenting this
culture for quite a long time what would
you say that you're you're at now are
you sounding the alarm do you think that
anything can be done to mitigate the
kind of the dangers that you've spelled
out yeah I mean I mean I've it's brother
this sort of sound the alarm because no
one's gonna listen right that's
the other trouble with the psychedelic
movement is its panting no muna
apparently which means you know not
subject to deference to Authority of any
shape or form it's why you know in the
50s and 60s the US Army studied dosing
soldiers to see if they could use it as
a disorient on the battlefield and you
know one of the unintended side effects
was a budget you should have a bunch of
enlisted dudes were like what the
am i doing in this uniform and I'm gonna
put this gun down and I'm gonna go home
now so there I think that Jeremiah ants
you know from positions of authority
highly unlikely to work but what I would
say is actually more rather than a
warning about more of a clarion call
which is hey good news folks is we have
access to a higher concentration of
ecstatic and transformative technologies
social technologies than any humans ever
have on the planet . and we may not have
the luxury to linger in the transition
and you can assign this you can say hey
these are both changes and higher-order
things all conspiring to provide us
these tools at this time you know send
some folks do sometimes we'll make a
case that like ayahuasca hasn't in an
agency and them intelligence right and
it's coming into this world not unlike
the Dalai Lama saying hey the Chinese
had to come and do horrendous things in
our country to blow us out of Tibet of
that isolation to bring the Dhamma to
the West you know kind of just so
stories of the psychedelic Renaissance I
don't think you have to go there you
could just simply say hey man shit's
happening and it's here but it's here
just in a time and we might not get the
chance to gawk and dawdle in the magic
and wonder of our own transformations it
may be like here's the tools folks wake
yourself up rip the band-aid off
and and you know get your wobbly legs
about you and then you're needed like we
are needed this is not to become this
self obsessive recursive endless
personal journey game maybe the hippies
got to try that we don't we're all
needed and we're needed at full strength
and not just in ourselves but within for
each other and so that would be my if I
had anything to share it would be that
like we've got the tools now we have to
use the
and there's not a moment to spare
great claiming thank you
[Music]
you